<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Read my blog | Enrico Teotti</title>
    <description>agile coach, (visual) facilitator with a background in software development and product management since 2001 in Europe, Australia and the US.
</description>
    <link>http://teotti.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://teotti.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 16:19:10 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 16:19:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star Wars Agile Retrospectives a Principle 12 Story</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many folks love themed retrospectives a popular one I often see is around Star Wars. Here’s my take at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be good to check with your group before using a franchise might not relate to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simplify this article I’ll describe the container for this Retrospective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a team of 5/6 people involved (better if somewhat familiar with the Star Wars franchise)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two weeks iteration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Retrospective focused on “what can we make to make our work even more effective”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll provide links to Mural, Miro and Google Slides template to help you run this a Star Wars flavored Agile Retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: there are some minor spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-the-engines&quot;&gt;Starting the engines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have Kerth’s Prime directive printed in a Star Wars scrolling text to set the mood. There is a deep purpose behind the Prime directive, you can read my toughts in two extensive articles on &lt;a href=&quot;http://teotti.com/challenge-agile-retrospectives-prime-directive/&quot;&gt;Challenging the directive&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://teotti.com/analyze-kerth-prime-directive/&quot;&gt;Dissecting the directive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would then continue setting the stage, to allow the group to connect with each other and with the last iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am using a variation of ESVP. I put at the bottom of the spectrum Finn a good folk forced in to being a Storm Trooper, it’s but with potential for redemption aka re-engagement. The reason is to ensure we don’t create a us vs them that is predominant in the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which identity represents how you feel about this retrospective?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Storm Trooper: I don’t wanna be here but this is what I’ve always done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mandalorian: Not sure why we’re here. This is an ok break in-between bounty hunting contracts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rebel Alliance member: I am here to work together for a better future for the galaxy!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jedi: I want to leave no stone unturned and bring more light to the next iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a bunch of Storm Troopers and Mandalorians… you might want to switch your focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step1.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick a space ship that indicates how the last iteration was for you&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am using a variation of the “pick a form of transportation that represents the last iteration for you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AT-AT&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Millenium Falcon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X-Wing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DeathStar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can explore the differences, why people picked their choice, or simply acknowledge them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step1.2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-at-what-happened&quot;&gt;Looking at what happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I create questions to gather data that connect to the metaphor and to the team. This is what I mostly saw in the “Fun Star Wars Retrospectives” with a jump to what can we do about it which is linear thinking and taps in business as usual mind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add a fun spin to “no naming no blaming” with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To prevent bounty hunters contract, it’s our policy to avoid people’s names and rather point to systems and sub-systems. ie. rather then saying: “Luke messed up the database on Monday” we should use “the database got Error Code: 1117. Too many columns after adding one column to its 1699”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the prompts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What was turning off our hyperdrive? (frustrating)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did we blow up the Death Star? How?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What felt like a trap? Why was it a trap? (surprise)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where was the force bringing the best out of us? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where was the dark side bringing the worst out of us? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I like to give a few minutes to let the group asking questions about the meaning of some cards. We do not jump to solutioning yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those prompts are phrased to explore what we saw rather then where we want to go. That’s coming up next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-we-sense&quot;&gt;What do we sense?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s move those cards and create a map, do we see any patterns? Do they have names?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of this you should have clusters of themes and patterns and some stand alone cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step2.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-we-do-about-it&quot;&gt;What can we do about it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which cluster shall we focus on? Which one would make our team work more effectively?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we want this Agile Retrospective outcome to destroy a tie-fighter or defeat the empire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s reflect for 5 minutes and think of ideas that can reduce the negative patterns and radiate the positives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we come up with a thoughtful but actionable plan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we’re hinting at the group if we want to focus on simple, complicated or complex issues. I use a Star Wars metaphor for that. See my &lt;a href=&quot;http://teotti.com/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/&quot;&gt;Cynefin helps retrospectives&lt;/a&gt; article for more background on difference between these domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the group replies: “we defeat the Empire by destroying all Tie fighters” you might need to to explore linearity and complexity with them. Short answer is, even if you destroy tie-fighters they’ll build more. To free the galaxy, at some point we will need to shift the Empire power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of this you should have ideas on what to do for your patterns and stand alone cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-the-force-in-your-next-action-item&quot;&gt;Use the FORCE in your next action item!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the time to make those ideas actionable. I came up with a FORCE acronym:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First step: what is the first step of this plan?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Observable: what is an observable result that the first step is positively influencing the system? What is an observable result of it negatively influencing the system?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Responsibility: who is responsible to check on this plan progress?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Controllable: is the first step something within the team control zone?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy: how much energy do we have for this first step?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the acronym to get an idea of what action is the one to carry over. Perhaps use a poll to decide which one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once one or two actions are defined you can start closing your Retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-was-the-time-spent-in-this-retrospective&quot;&gt;How was the time spent in this Retrospective?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variation of Esther’s Plus Delta Return On Time Invested:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0 - Jar Jar Binks - This was a complete waste of time &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 - Jabba the Hutt - I learned one thing, but this was mostly a waste of time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 - Bobba Fett - I got paid back for the effort I put in to this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 - Han Solo - I got a lot more out of this then I expected!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 - Luke Skywalker - This was amazing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea that would have made you vote one point higher, and one thing you liked about today Retro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/step5.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And boom, there goes the Death Start and you have an Agile Retrospective and freedom in the Galaxy. For this iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing a metaphor to your Agile Retrospective can switch things up but you must have a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Fun retrospective sounds are just another variation to the put data in n-columns + action items. A style that fosters linear thinking and jumping from Gather data to Decide what to do skipping focus on a critical step: Generate insights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I hope I outlined the difference between the two approaches: exercising divergent thinking on a prioritized topic or theme before deciding what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linear thinking is now always bad. It’s great to tackle simple or complicated problems. When applied to complex or wicked problems it can (and does) backfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have you read from this post that made you shake your head in disagreement? What made you nod in approval? What challenges would you face with this Star Wars themes Agile Retrospective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a Mural template for you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.mural.co/template/a7827f2d-4584-4afe-9001-55e83efc13dd/8b74b81c-adde-4dc1-be91-cdfe31f5560b&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/mural-template.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a Mural fan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1X9U0Ik4Q0dR8PMchGKV4jFPaV6tcOkQ_gSUcv5C3IP0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Google Slides template&lt;/a&gt; you have to clone it to your own drive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_kx2R6sk=/&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; Let me know if you’d like to use it. They make it extra lengthy to provide templates publish to their Miroverse… :(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ps
All product names, character names, illustrations, logos, and brands are property of their respective owners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/star-wars-agile-retrospectives-a-principle-12-story/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>facilitation</category>
        
        <category>retrospectives</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cynefin helps Agile Retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you feel like your Agile Retrospective is only tackling low hanging fruit and missing out on real improvements? Have you ever wondered if in your retro you’re dealing with clear, complicated or complex issues? In this article I’ll share the way I’ve tackled that using concepts from Cognitive Edge’s Cynefin and other frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;What?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start describing a popular Agile Retrospective approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You gather data about your last iteration–or retrospective theme–then you might move in to generating insights to have the group do some sense-making to create action items to make their work more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/retro-step-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is usually a question to the group: “Do you see any patterns in the data?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/retro-step-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s assuming the facilitator doesn’t facipulate and create clusters and make decisions for the group. Don’t do that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/facipulation.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually see a prioritization, brief discussions about the clusters or cards leading to “is there something we can do about this?” if no let’s move on, if yes jump to define action items for the item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/retro-step-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;popular-agile-retrospective-approach-works-for-clear-or-complicated-issues&quot;&gt;Popular Agile Retrospective approach works for clear or complicated issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This popular Agile Retrospective approach–I’ve seen it in 90% of teams–&lt;strong&gt;is adequate for the items or clusters that are in an ordered domain where there is link–or a chain of links–between cause and effect&lt;/strong&gt;. Here linear thinking where a plan–a series of actions–can fix their root cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cynefin defines those as ordered domains. In &lt;strong&gt;clear&lt;/strong&gt; you can create an action item a best practice a process that will work everytime and fix the issue. Here you sense, categorize, respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-clear.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cynefin calls &lt;strong&gt;complicated&lt;/strong&gt; where the link between cause and effect is a chain. There are stable patterns that an expert or study can analyze. Here you sense, analyze, respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-complicated.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who decides which domain you’re in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/facipulation.gif&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert it should not be the scrum master and it should not be the teach lead. It should be a group sense-making that leads to finding the right granularity and consensus on what we’re dealing with. Later I introduce a couple of ways your group can practically determine if topics are clear, complicated or complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-brief-story-about-root-causes&quot;&gt;A brief story about root causes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simplified example adapted from a real life production incident I witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me introduce James and Anna. They both work at Acme Inc, James with devops, Anna software developer within our team. They’re not in the same nation. They never met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a Cloud configuration repository with the configurations for all the apps in the cloud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is an App repository that Anna and her team work on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anna pushes a change to the app Cloud configuration repository with a “{cipher}encrypted code” line to enable a new feature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The App update with the code to use cypher is not on master but that doesn’t matter since the team run their own deployments not devops. Production deploy is gonna happen in a day or two anyways.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James is running a cluster wide security update that triggers an automatic redeploy of all apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;App is deployed with the new Cloud config but runs on old code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;App fails, production is down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where is the root cause of this failure? Hold on to that thought I am introducing a quote that might influence you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When we look at problems only as scientific or technical in nature, removed from the context to which they are responding, they may be complicated, but they generally can be solved through straightforward, scientific and engineering design models.
But, when we understand these problems as embedded within human contexts that organize themselves through changing social, political, economic, and cultural belief systems, we are in the realm of complexity”.
Design Unbound – Designing for emergence in a white water world&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does that mean? If you look at code in a vacuum you can and will find the root cause of a bug. If you’re trying to reduce the number of bugs–or production incidents–on your project you’re not gonna “fix it” by fixing the root causes of those incidents. It will keep coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this incident–the last of many involving devops and Acme’s software development cycle–I heard leadership say that devops were “borderline incompetent”. Would it be any different if they said Anna was borderline incompetent? Or that Anna and James are borderline incompetent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to blame Anna or James or their lack of “best practices”. There is always an expert that will tell you that. It’s much more interesting to look at the context of that incident and reflect if we see any patterns and how can we influence them. Influencing the issue to use a safe to fail approach (resilience) rather then failsafe (perfection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first important step in our Agile Retrospectives is for the group–and the wider organization–to appreciate that &lt;strong&gt;the issues we face are not all the same and we can’t tackle them all with best practices or experts fixing the root cause&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-domains.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-complex-domains&quot;&gt;In complex domains&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the high number of agents and relationships you can’t use analytic techniques or categorization. Here we can only perceive (not predict) emergent patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-complex-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we try to predict them with retrospective coherence and prepare a procedure to “fix it” as soon as the emergent pattern shows up in a differnt way the procedure will be useless or harmful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-complex-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important for the group to zoom in and zoom out, help the group find an adequate granularity and determine if what we’re tackling in our Agile Retrospectives is a clear or complicated (something that can be tackled with linear thinking) or instead a complex or chaotic issue that needs a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Complexity Cynefin talks about probe, sense, respond. The probing part is looking for patterns in your gathered data, the sense is a reflection to make sense of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-complex-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the sense making is a response, an experiment with an hypothesis (classic retros call it action item). We define signs of success and failure so we can radiate the experiment or dampen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this space you can use approaches like Polarity Management or Adaptive Action cycles. These are NOT activities but rather approaches to tackle a wicked problem (that’s how complex problems are sometime referred as).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-chaotic-domain&quot;&gt;In chaotic domain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no time to probe and you can only intervene decisively to reduce the turbulence. You will then sense the system’s reacted perhaps shifting the system or subsystem to another domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-chaos.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-what-should-i-do-in-my-agile-retrospective&quot;&gt;Now what should I do in my Agile Retrospective?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you gather the data while you generate insights do you let the group do some &lt;strong&gt;sensing on what they see&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you tried to introduce the Cynefin domains and use them as a categorization framework? Introduce the framework first then see where individuals put cards in the domains, be curious about the ones that appear in multiple domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you tried a contextualized Cynefin framework? Use prompts to build a framework from the data or use activities like 4 points to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-4-points.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an alternative to Cynefin you can approach the sense making in generate insights with Stacey Matrix which has horizontal axis for Close and Far from certainty and a vertical axis for Close and Far from agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve identified issues in a complex domain, probed for patterns &lt;strong&gt;let the group prepare an experiment with an hypothesis to define the granularity at which you want to influence the issue, your next wise step and your expected sign of success and possible signs of failure&lt;/strong&gt;. You could even specify amplification actions and dampening actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-power-is-in-the-sense-making-and-dialogue&quot;&gt;The power is in the sense making and dialogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find powerful is the dialogue and sense making that follows. Individuals might have different opinions of where things live, inviting to duplicate clusters and topics that are seen as simple, complicated and complex by different people creates valuable differences that when highlighted can help the whole group figure out what kinda of issue they’re dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/cynefin-shared-language.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s the real sense making. That’s where a retrospective gets past the low hanging fruit and in to deeper issues&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warning-about-this-approach-to-agile-retrospectives&quot;&gt;Warning about this approach to Agile Retrospectives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sense-making and creating an experiment can take time and tends to cut the focus on low hanging fruit (which can also be valuable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the only time to deal with low hanging fruit is during the Agile Retrospective I suggest a shorter daily practice to talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treating all issues with a linear cause and effect approach can be detrimental. You might fix some of the low hanging fruit but the underlying patterns won’t be influenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When generating insights in your Agile Retrospective spend time reflecting on what kinda of issues we’re looking at, use Cynefin as a binocular to look at things from different angles. Are we in a ordered domain? Are we in complexity? Are we in chaos? Do not facipulate, disinter-mediate the sense making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kinda of sense making do you run in your retrospectives? In what domains is your group tackling most issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cognitive-edge.com/videos/cynefin-framework-introduction/&quot;&gt;Cynefin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/resources/adaptive-action.html&quot;&gt;HSD Adaptive action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/288117.Polarity_Management&quot;&gt;Polarity Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>facilitation</category>
        
        <category>retrospectives</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Questions to ponder when Agile Retrospectives are missing reflection</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I was on a reoccurring call with Human System Dynamics (HSD) associates and friends where a volunteer shares a wicked issue they have and then listen to questions without answering. &lt;strong&gt;The questions are open ended, not disguised advice, beyond the knowledge of the asker&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope these questions will help you see a next step for your Agile Retrospective missing reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Answers have short shelf lives in complex systems, and a good question can last a lifetime.
-Glenda Eoyang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After that the person considers a next wise action that is within control, reasonable, promising, short term response&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The groups follows HSD simple rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stand in inquiry
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn judgment in to curiosity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn conflict in to shared exploration&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn defensiveness into self-reflection&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn assumptions in to questions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for true and useful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find the energy in difference&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zoom in and zoom out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connect with stories and impacts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Celebrate life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-wicked-issue&quot;&gt;What is a wicked issue?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how HSD defines it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Massive interdependencies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fuzzy boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeating but never exactly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No root cause&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cannot be solved, but can be influenced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some graphics I created to explain the process in a micro talk I gave:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/questions-to-ponder-when-agile-retrospectives-are-missing-reflection/aa-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/questions-to-ponder-when-agile-retrospectives-are-missing-reflection/aa-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-wicked-issue&quot;&gt;My wicked issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Retrospectives are times to reflect with your team. You can use Adaptive Action, but many people jump from WHAT to NOW WHAT. They miss the time of reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-questions-i-received&quot;&gt;The questions I received&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What does time have to do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JK: What kind of false time lines do we put on ourselves and our teams?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What if you started with the SO WHAT and left out the WHAT and NOW WHAT once?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: Where else do you see that lack of reflection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : How many different tools and models exist to support SO WHAT?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What do feelings have to do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BMC : Are there other spaces or processes where the team is capable of doing reflection? What’s different?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JJ : If you can apply only ONE simple rule (HSD) to trigger off the introspection, what would it be?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SB : Building on MKS.is there judgment usually at play?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: What kinds of invitation do you have and how do people know what to reflect on?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : Are there some people who are better at SO WHAT than others are?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BMC : Are they aware that they are skipping the step?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SB : where  might they do so what elsewhere?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JK: How does our current educational system teach and promote reflection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LP : What pattern(s) are these reflection times intended to generate?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EMN : Have you worked with a team that does  reflection intuitively and what is different about that team?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: Is engaging in retrospective a finite game or an infinite game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MKS : What is your So What on the teams not doing a So What?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JJ : What is the “fear” behind the skipping Reflection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SB : What’s the normative truth about the so what?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : How is the retrospective about individual and how about team performance?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JJ : Is time/urgency more important than quality?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : How would a retrospective work if it were totally in inquiry?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: How do your team members understand or use the inquiry practices?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SB : what do they really want to know?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EMN : Are there any fun games that require reflection?  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What would a prospective look like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: How would we turn some of the models and methods into games?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MKS : Would the team even do a retrospective, if given the choice?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What would happen if you took this wicked issue to the group?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : What does it have to do with learning?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LP : What role do questions play in a retrospective?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH: What’s the difference between an invitation and a “rule”?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : Who wins the retrospective game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GE : Where besides Agile world does this issue happen?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SB : What are the simple rules that govern how the retrospective is done now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this session, it was comforting hearing similar questions to the ones I am asking and the different ones that I didn’t explore yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those questions aren’t “disguised advice” but tokens to get to a deeper insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that there was a conversation with many interesting exchanged, somebody raised a good point about the &lt;strong&gt;downside of too much reflection&lt;/strong&gt;. That made me realize how some people have been burned–or are concerned–by analysis-paralysis and might be leaning towards action/reaction. &lt;strong&gt;That’s why I find the adaptive action cycle step “Now what?” such a natural and important one&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-what&quot;&gt;Now what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that stuck most for me was “why do you care about this?”. It took me a little to reply and the answer is I want to leave the world in a better place than I’ve found it, and fostering reflection is for me a way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clearing out why I care gave me more energy in making Agile Retrospectives the tool they’re meant to be and not just a checkbox.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did those questions resonate with you? Do they inspire you to a wise next step on your Agile Retrospectives that are lacking reflection? Do they make you see your current issue differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the next &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/learning-opportunities/adaptive-action-labs/inquiry-is-the-answer-covid-19.html&quot;&gt;“Inquiry is the answer”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/about-hsd-institute/simple-rules.html&quot;&gt;HSD simple rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/468635936&quot;&gt;Watch this session’s recording&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/questions-to-ponder-when-agile-retrospectives-are-missing-reflection/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/questions-to-ponder-when-agile-retrospectives-are-missing-reflection/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>facilitation</category>
        
        <category>retrospectives</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How I ask for questions while facilitating online</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember when but I always knew when I asked questions without giving enough time for answers. I think I did it because I couldn’t stand the silence. &lt;strong&gt;I think I also tought if you have a question you better be quick cause we’re working here!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I transitioned to a coaching role, with software developers, product managers and leadership I tweaked that &lt;strong&gt;quite&lt;/strong&gt; a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this blog post will help you reflect on how you’re asking questions online and in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wait-20-seconds&quot;&gt;Wait 20 seconds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I ask a question in an online call–with or without video–my default is to count in my head between 5 to 20 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give people time to reflect on the question and come up with replies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I count like one-thousand-and-one, one-thousand-and-two and so on. I am cool with the uncomfortable silence. I am actually excited as I wait for questions. Ask yourself: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Am I ok with uncomfortable silence?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always 20 seconds? Nope. Someone one told me always and never don’t apply to facilitation. And I reply “it’s depends”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the group is small (say 4/5) and I see all faces shaking no I cut it short and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On some video call platforms you can ask for non verbal feedback–ie raise hand for questions but on online calls larger then 10/15 I still rather wait it out and give people time to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;syncronous-vs-asyncronous&quot;&gt;Syncronous vs asyncronous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people might not feel comfortable speaking up in from of the whole group. Or simply need more time to reflect on what the question they have. Asking to write down–in the chat, in your virtual space–can help with that and the latter can give anononymity too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use asyncronous in groups larger then 5/6, after I see a few popping up I ask would anyone like to share their question? If nobody starts I just go ahead read the post it and answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find especially useful to use the async for debriefing activities or questions for groups larger then 10/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-ask-questions&quot;&gt;How to ask questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably not great to ask “everything is clear right?” wait 1 second and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I avoid leading questions, good way to ask for feedback would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is there any question? (duh)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is it clear to everybody what we’re doing next? – after a brief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imagine you applied this in your context, what questions would come up for you? – after some more theoretical piece&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after looking at a set of data might be a good fit to use the questions from Adaptive action (HSD’s set of powerful question that lead to wise action): Where are you now? Where would you like to be? How are you gonna get there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-note-on-emergence&quot;&gt;A note on emergence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In facilitating emerging activities–that are left purpusefully vague and open–I avoid the questions above since they would give too much guidance. I explain at the best of my abilities and then ask “raise your hand if you have enough information to be able to get to work”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you’ve found something useful, where are you know in your asking questions online journey? Where would you like to be? How are you gonna get there? Let me know in the comments or on twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/how-i-ask-for-questions-while-facilitating-online/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/how-i-ask-for-questions-while-facilitating-online/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>facilitation</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From software engineer to visualizer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll describe my journey in to the visualization world with links to resources that helped in my progression and that I wish I had on day 1. My background has been 18 years of sofware development with no art and minimal drawing or sketching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you think you lack the artistic skill read on, visualization techniques like sketchnoting and visual facilitation &lt;strong&gt;are not art&lt;/strong&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visualization journey started about two years ago. I currently use visualization for facilitation, presentations, sketchnoting. Let me show you some or &lt;a href=&quot;#list-of-visualization-resources&quot;&gt;jump to the list of resources&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/digital.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yes you can do it digitally!&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/example.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Visual presentation&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/happy-birthday-yvan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketchnote of a virtual birthday call&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/open-space-session.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of an open space session I hosted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-common-background&quot;&gt;Our common background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in our life we were drawing. And we were having fun at it. Until some of us stopped because someone–probably a teacher or a parent–said the drawing is not good enough anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did we also stop writing? We’re still sending emails and text messages, writing reminders even if we did not excell in writing classes. We wouldn’t think to stop writing just cause someone said it’s not up to par anymore :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, learning visualization it’s totally doable because we’ve already done it! :)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me it all started when I attended Alberto Brandolini’s workshop on Event Storming and saw his initial slide with “Event Storming masterclass” title and a swimming pool, he said “my approach to teach Event Storming is to trow you in the swimmingpool”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/visualization-event-storming.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the class I asked about it and someone in the group said “oh yeah that’s visual presentation… it’s easy just follow a few rules and you’ll get it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My head exploded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was I didn’t have a list of URLs or books! So this blog post is the list I wish I had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;list-of-visualization-resources&quot;&gt;List of Visualization resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first free resource I’d reccomand is &lt;a href=&quot;http://educationaltoolsportal.eu/en/visual-facilitation-cookbook&quot;&gt;Visual Facilitation cookbook&lt;/a&gt;. Made from the ERASMUs program it has a lot of good tips on how to get started with visualization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second I’d reccomand to start practicing! You don’t need fancy markers! Follow the booklet and practice! I started with mindmaps of meetings I was in. The purpose was to keep me engaged and to have some visuals to see where the conversation went. Little by little I started adding pictograms on some nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third I’d reccomand Benjamin Felis class &lt;a href=&quot;https://graphic-recording-and-visual-facilitation.teachable.com/p/communicate-with-visuals-your-new-super-power?affcode=297856_zgdjgkfq&quot;&gt;Communicate with visuals – your new super power!&lt;/a&gt; a 120 Euro video class. Totally worth it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next I’d reccomand &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikablo.com/blog/2017/09/18/uzmo-thinking-with-your-pen-the-bikablo-visualisation-guide-now-in-english/&quot;&gt;UZMO Thinking with your pen&lt;/a&gt;. It guides in understand why are you visualizing? What’s your goal? What’s the context? On top of all that it gives very practical advice on how to create composite pictograms, approaches templates. Very solid. Only downside I see they are very specific on the Bikablo technique which is not the only way you can visualize :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After that I’d reccomand &lt;a href=&quot;https://davidsibbet.com/visual-meetings-book/&quot;&gt;Visual Meetings by David Sibbet&lt;/a&gt;. It helped me–as a facilitator–see the larger picture of where visualization fits in meetings–I actually read it before UZMO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this list helps someone out there :) What’s stopping you from starting visualizing? What resources have you used to start your journey? Leave comments or hit me up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/agenteo&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/from-software-engineer-to-visualizer/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reduce your network utilization on Zoom calls</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is for folks using a PC or a Mac spending lots of time (and network utilization) on Zoom calls. Do you know how fast your Internet is? Do you know how much traffic are Zoom calls are chewing up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found out today (using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wireshark.org&quot;&gt;Wireshark&lt;/a&gt;) on OSX 10.15.5 is the gallery view in Zoom (tested with 5.0.2) generates a lot more (3 times) traffic on a 12 person call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted you might wanna see people on most of your call there might be situations where you want to reduce your traffic by compromising that experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll assume you use two monitor windows. If you’re not following me on twitter (and missing out on all those zoom and agile retrospectives nerdy comments) this is the option you’ll need to reduce your network:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;You might already know but Zoom has a dual window / dual monitor feature to allow you to split the video or the screen share from the gallery view. First pic is the speaker on window 1 and gallery on window 2. Second pic, is the shared screen on window 1 and gallery window 2. HTH &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/DXTHodUcIq&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DXTHodUcIq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 𝐸𝓃𝓇𝒾𝒸𝑜 𝒯𝑒𝑜𝓉𝓉𝒾 (@agenteo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/agenteo/status/1256572194181787650?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 2, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have two Zoom windows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gallery view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;speaker view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by minimizing the gallery view you will reduce Zoom’s traffic and still see the active speaker on your second Zoom window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/reduce-your-network-utilization-on-zoom-calls/hero.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/reduce-your-network-utilization-on-zoom-calls/zoom-on-network-reduction.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be able to achieve the same reduction with a single window and hide all gallery speakers but I did not test it. Does this trick works on Windows? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/reduce-your-network-utilization-on-zoom-calls/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/reduce-your-network-utilization-on-zoom-calls/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The law of two feet in open space online</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is for facilitators holding space and organizers of Open Space events that moved–or want to move–online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article assumes you know what Open Space Technology is and participated in a physical one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of the article is to share my experience with the “law of two feet” in an online space and I reflect on preparation of online open spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a physical open space you probably experienced getting up and walking to another session when you felt you were not contributing or you were not getting anything out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Briefly stated, this law says that every individual has two feet, and must be prepared to use them. Responsibility for a successful outcome in any Open Space Event resides with exactly one person—each participant. Individuals can make a difference and must make a difference. If that is not true in a given situation, they, and they alone, must take responsibility to use their two feet, and move to a new place where they can make a difference.” - https://annualexchange.com/2018/06/30/the-law-of-two-feet/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does “law of two feet” translate when you are in an open space event that moved online? By the way I am not sure if we should still call it Open Space but that’s for another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;responsibility-for-a-successful-outcome-in-any-open-space-event-resides-with-exactly-one-personeach-participant&quot;&gt;Responsibility for a successful outcome in any Open Space Event resides with exactly one person—each participant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;they, and they alone, must take responsibility to use their two feet, and move to a new place where they can make a difference&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Works in a physical open space. We all know how to go from point A to point B. But what about online? Does all my audience know where to click how to navigate to other rooms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images//the-law-of-two-feet-in-open-space-online//5x2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I am so stuck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-you-know-how-to-get-to-another-session&quot;&gt;Do you know how to get to another session?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first time as a &lt;strong&gt;session host&lt;/strong&gt; in open space online, after welcoming the group I asked “do you know how to get to another session?”. I think that’s of paramount importance but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as an &lt;strong&gt;openspace organizer&lt;/strong&gt; I can’t expect all session hosts to do that. Some might not think about that, some might have a million other things happening as they’re hosting and some might simply cling to their audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an &lt;strong&gt;openspace organizer&lt;/strong&gt; I must prepare the space to account for the “the law of clicks”. I first heard that name from Gerardo De Luzenberger from the italian chapter of IAF. It means moving to another session with just a couple of mouse clicks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-law-of-two-clicks&quot;&gt;The law of two clicks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerardo and IAF run for a few weeks an open space #FACILITA2020 event with about 100 people and used &lt;a href=&quot;https://qiqochat.com/about&quot;&gt;QiQo chat&lt;/a&gt;. Qiqo chat seaminglessly assigns Zoom rooms to your open space sessions and it reduces risk for the audience to make mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You still have to account for individuals that might not see Zoom messages and having technical difficulties. &lt;strong&gt;I don’t think there is a one size fits all technical solution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could have an online spreadsheet–or slide or text document–with a list of Zoom room URLs (or Google Meet or Jitsi ot whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is my audience able to add and navigate those without messing up other meeting IDs? What’s my contigency if Jack accidentally deletes Luke’s meeting URL? A backchannel? Is everybody aware/invited?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could let the session organizers self-organize and pick their remote video call tool.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the audience be familiar with those tools? And willing to perhaps install a new one? &lt;strong&gt;The online agile coach camp coming up in August addressed that by asking all participant to bring their personal (free) Zoom Account to (I assume) have sessions hosts create personal meetings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the video call tool, there must be a clear way for the participants to view current sessions and navigate between rooms and to communicate with me (the organizer) when they have technical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;every individual is &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; clicks away from another room, and must be prepared to click. Responsibility for a successful outcome resides with exactly one person—each participant. Individuals can make a difference and must make a difference. If that is not true in a given situation, they, and they alone, must take responsibility to use their two clicks, and move to a new place where they can make a difference &lt;strong&gt;or ask for help&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many clicks does my audience need to get to another room?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-click-bus-experiment&quot;&gt;The click bus experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An experiement I conducted to assess how the law of two feet translated online was the click bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in an open space with over 80 people and I hosted a session called the “click bus” virtually moving around the online open space sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The click bus’ purpose was to help folks stuck in open space online rooms to navigate and move to other rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The click bus group met in a Zoom call where we assigned a head and tail member. The bus head would tell the click bus participants what was the next stop, make sure we all understood then be the first to leave. The tail would wait for all members to be out of the current room, and be the last to leave for the next room. Both head and tail were tech savvy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The click bus had a dedicated backchannel (we used a free online chat called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.e-chat.co&quot;&gt;http://www.e-chat.co&lt;/a&gt;) so we wouldn’t disturb the conversation or chat of the rooms we visited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in the new room the bus head would silently announce to the session participants that the click bus arrived. That was done either in the chat or via videocamera post-it. The announce would include an invite for people that wanted to leave with a link to the backchannel chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone (beside the head and tail volunteers) were free to leave and stay in the visited room–or go anwhere else–at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clickbus could be run &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; the space opens as a technical pre-check activity or offered as a service to bring some of the human contact you get walking around in a physical open space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With about 20 years of software development and product management I really don’t have a problem moving around but &lt;strong&gt;COVID made me realise even more how many folks are having technical trouble out there&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As an open space organizer we must provide support mechanisms to avoid folks feeling stupid for not “getting it”, which could be the case if we said “whatever happens is the only thing that could happen. If we support the audience there is a better chance they will contribute and enjoy it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, people might be calling from tablets, Windows, OSX so as organizers we need to be ready / aware to deal with technical difficulties on different systems. Do we ask the audience to run a speed test before the event? What do we do if out of 300 people 150 have dialup? Do we change our setup accordingly? How do we support people with slower connections?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there is a one size fits all solution, but I think we need to do better and prepare for our audience. What are you doing to make it better for your participants?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/the-law-of-two-feet-in-open-space-online/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/the-law-of-two-feet-in-open-space-online/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Video call from your LAN during COVID-19</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this short blog I explain how to have great video calls with nearby–within your wifi signal range–people. This avoids going out and back from the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself in my house in my Italian home town (with a shitty internet connection). Family lives in a house next to me and we share the same (shitty) wifi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of covid we’re trying to avoid contact and calling via internet has been tedious and really really unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So guess what you can use your local area network to video call and message. For free. And it’ll take about 5 minutes to setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal was to install a simple app on phone / computer and allow the communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked in to two solutions: jitsi and linphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jitsi&quot;&gt;Jitsi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is web based, used WebRTC, really cool project BUT you need a centralized server. Great &lt;a href=&quot;https://jitsi.org/news/new-tutorial-installing-jitsi-meet-on-your-own-linux-server/&quot;&gt;explanation on how to set it up from skratch on Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; they also have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jitsi/docker-jitsi-meet&quot;&gt;docker container&lt;/a&gt; that is plug and play. I was able to setup and test locally the http version in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linphone&quot;&gt;Linphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos to Stefano Zaglio that pointed me to &lt;a href=&quot;http://linphone.org/&quot;&gt;linphone&lt;/a&gt;. OMG it’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has android, ios, osx, windows, linux clients and it does not require a server!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am almost done with the post. Install linphone on your device!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do not need to sign up for an account. Once installed you will have a SIP address like this: &lt;code&gt;sip:enrico@192.168.1.3:5060&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to start chatting you need to comunicate the sip address to your pal (or viceversa).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quick-gotchas&quot;&gt;Quick gotchas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your device SIP address uses your local IP. In my experience wifi AP are generally keeping your IP the same (linked to your MAC address) but it’s possible for it to change. In that case your pal on the other side won’t be able to contact you anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have multiple devices iphone, ipad, mac the other person has to add each SIP address to her contacts. It’s a bit like having multiple extensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this helps some folks out there. I think offloading the internet of local communications makes sense. I can see SIP as a way to connect to your elderly neighbour that might not have a recent phone Let me know how your experiment goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/video-call-from-your-LAN-during-covid19/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/video-call-from-your-LAN-during-covid19/</guid>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What happens before an agile retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I share what happens before I facilitate an agile retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most team I joined approach retrospectives as something that has to be done once a week in 1 hour and you don’t need any preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience that’s when retrospectives yield more basic results and in the worst cases become counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before a retrospective–any meeting in my opinion–you must prepare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted you can’t come up with a plan that’s perfect. You work in a complex adaptive system so be ready for the unexpected. But you can take care of some due diligence and I’ll explain my approach in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question is what’s your role? Are you an external facilitator? A team member? A lead developer, product manager scrum master? If you feel like you’re overstepping your role by following this advice maybe treat it like an experiment. See how it goes. For the longest time I was a developer when I designed and facilitated my team retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re all biased but if you’re a scrum master or a team member probably even more. Be aware of that and maybe ask for a co-facilitator or co-designer external to the team.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-there-a-retrospective-purpose&quot;&gt;Is there a retrospective purpose?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With teams of 6/10 I like to run short 1:1s or watercooler convos about what’s on the team member’s minds. If I see a pattern I propose that as the retrospective theme before the retrospective. Always check with the group before making that call final and designing the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip I learned the hard way: When you focus your retrospective on a theme you must have a way for the little low hanging fruit to be tackled. I like to do that in short 10/15m daily retrospectives. Those are action item focused. The themed retrospective is focused on reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme might be coming from the person “leading” the team, or if you’re an external facilitator from the stakeholder that brought you in. If you have time try to check in with the team anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That theme should hint at the purpose. &lt;strong&gt;You can do this investigation inside a retrospective that has purpose of “improving what we did this iteration” but you’d spend time doing that sifting instead of reflecting.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s very contextual sometime you might want the group to do that but in my experience I prefer to prepare a theme before. And if the group has a topic or a theme emerging different than what was planned I go with it. It’s their meeting. If the majority of the room expresses desire to explore other direction. This is where you–the facilitator–need to get out of the group’s way. &lt;strong&gt;If you’re a product manager, scrum master, tech lead that’s gonna be very hard to let go of your bias and your agenda&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is the retrospective design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-retrospective-design&quot;&gt;The retrospective design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so that you don’t pick a random format on retromat print it and walk in the retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few questions that I like to ask once the theme is defined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who’s gonna be there?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are we taking their time?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we want to get out of this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How are we getting there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last question is where I design the retrospective with activities that fit the group and the context. &lt;strong&gt;This is the plan and no plan survives contact with the enemy. So don’t be married to it.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s where the complexity of this facilitation job is. And why I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Void of context they might not give a lot of insights but these are examples of retrospectives design I helped other folks with. Those sessions would take anything from 15 minutes to 30/40 minutes. Groups size were between 6 to 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This helped a new facilitator gently shift away from pure mad/sad/glad whack-a-mole retro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This retrospective design was focused on a specific incident. I asked a bit of the history and then I designed the retro with the person calling the meeting.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This retrospective design was focused on manager / reports dynamics.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-2.1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Digging out some of the topics.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-2.10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This section was focused on way to visualize their current experiements data.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-2.20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;We came up with using colors and post it-s divided in pies to quickly eyeball data.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://teotti.com/assets/article_images/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/design-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This is from a leadership offsite that I didn&#39;t facilitate. This person asked to bounce off ideas and I believe we came up with a better structure. A reminder to ask for help when you&#39;re designing your sessions!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I sparked some intrest in dedicating some time finding a theme and designing your next retrospective? Are you already doing it? How much time do you dedicate to it? Who helps you? Leave a comment or a tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/what-happens-before-an-agile-retrospective/</guid>
        
        <category>retrospectives</category>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>agile</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Make your retrospective facilitation even more effective? Here&#39;s 4 things to look at</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I refer to retrospectives as a type of meeting inspired by the 12th agile principle “At regular intervals, the team reflects on how to become more effective, then tunes and adjusts its behavior accordingly.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many factors–specific to your context–can reduce the effectiveness of a retrospective and cause frustration and mistrust in the group. &lt;strong&gt;In this brief blog post I will describe how psychological safety, purpose, preparedness and collaboration can help make your retrospectives even more effective&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to highlight this is not a checklist. And depending on what system/subsystem your retrospective is working with you might need to switch between lens/approaches for complicated or complex domains. I’ll probably followup on that in a separate post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is for retrospective facilitators and regular team members that want to take on that role. You don’t need to be a trained facilitator, scrum master or product manager to introduce changes and make your retrospective even more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;psychological-safety&quot;&gt;Psychological Safety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amy Edmondson has done extensive research since the 90s on the subject–and published a book in 2018–&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Fearless-Organization-Psychological-Workplace-Innovation/dp/1119477247&quot;&gt;The Fearless Organization&lt;/a&gt;–Norm Kerth talks about a “Create Safety” exercise in his seminal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Project-Retrospectives-Handbook-Team-Reviews/dp/0932633447&quot;&gt;Project retrospectives&lt;/a&gt; book published in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt your retrospective is a blame game more than a reflection? Let me start from the foundation. &lt;strong&gt;Your retrospective outcomes will always be subpar if your team or organization does not support psychological safety&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people are punished when speaking up they will withhold information or play the blame game fostering a low energy retrospective. Improving psychological safety at the organizational level is outside the purpose of this post but &lt;strong&gt;there are strategies you can use to assess and improve psychological safety at the team level&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assess-the-team-psychological-safety&quot;&gt;Assess the team psychological safety&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by collecting data on the psychological safety level of the group. &lt;strong&gt;Try to have&lt;/strong&gt; one-on-ones with team members before the retrospective and take notes about their feelings.   &lt;strong&gt;Try to run an anonymous activity&lt;/strong&gt; (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://retromat.org/en/?id=1&quot;&gt;Explorer, Shopper, Vacationer, Prisoner&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://retromat.org/en/?id=130&quot;&gt;Elephant in the room&lt;/a&gt;) when you set the stage of your retrospective to anonymously collect the safety levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the the psychological safety level is low–say a room full of Prisoners in &lt;a href=&quot;https://retromat.org/en/?id=1https://retromat.org/en/?id=1&quot;&gt;ESVP&lt;/a&gt;–you should switch the focus of the retrospective to increase the safety level. Try to run an anonymous brainstorm on “what is one thing that would have to change to make you all not be prisoners?”. &lt;strong&gt;It’s possible that the outcome of the whole retrospective will be a team norm document to ensure people feel comfortable to speak up… and that’s great!&lt;/strong&gt; If you decide to continue with the original retrospective plan–despite a room full of disengaged folks–remind the group they will have a chance at the end of retro to provide feedback to make the next one safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;establish-a-safe-space-with-the-retrospective-prime-directive&quot;&gt;Establish a safe space with the Retrospective Prime Directive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a multitude of activities to set a safe stage for your retrospective, one is to read “The prime directive” by Norm Kerth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Regardless of what we discover, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some groups printing the directive, reading it and asking for a verbal “yes I believe it”–or alternatively “I believe for the duration/sake of this retrospective”–is sufficient to set a safe positive stage. In more dis-engaged groups some will say yes just to move on… but they truly believe someone messed up… they truly believe it’s someone’s fault. At times their fault. &lt;strong&gt;What do you believe as the facilitator?&lt;/strong&gt; If you–the retrospective facilitator–doubt the directive then it’s nonsensical to ask for a group agreement on it. You can read an article I wrote that &lt;a href=&quot;https://teotti.com/analyze-kerth-prime-directive/&quot;&gt;dissects the prime directive&lt;/a&gt; and better understand its roots. There is also a retrospective activity to &lt;a href=&quot;https://teotti.com/challenge-agile-retrospectives-prime-directive/&quot;&gt;challenge the retrospective&lt;/a&gt; prime directive with the group so instead of just a verbal yes you’d have a conversation about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prime directive is similar to bounded rationality and when embraced allows the group to shift from looking for a culprit to collaboratively looking at the context and generate insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-retrospective-purpose&quot;&gt;The retrospective purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If people don’t know why they’re in a retrospective and what they will get out of it they will be disengaged.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt your retro is more like a happy hour then a reflection? Very often teams go through the motions and always run retrospective to “reflect on what could be improved from the last iteration”. For a 3 or 4 people team and smaller challenges that could work for a little while but I’ve seen that purpose lead to premature convergence. I’ve seen retros where people would discuss for the same amount of time items like “someone left a glass on the desk and there is now mold in it” and “we should refactor the reservation class based on the application’s bounded contexts”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think spending 2 minutes discussing an item is not reflection. The problem I see is that people only share information during retrospective so you end up with a lot of those smaller items. I call whack-a-mole retrospective when the team generates lots of mad/sad/glad items and try to fix all the sad with rushed action items. The outcomes I’ve seen are too many action items–carrying over from one iteration to the next–and people never getting to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are at least a couple of options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;agree-on-a-real-time-agenda&quot;&gt;Agree on a real time agenda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check if the group is ok to try a retrospective with a real time agenda (aka &lt;a href=&quot;https://retromat.org/en/?id=51&quot;&gt;lean coffee&lt;/a&gt;). This helps because once the topics are listed the group can create clusters with a silent mapping activity, run a poll to prioritise what to talk about first. In this format the group decides if they want to keep talking about a topic of move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A critical piece–where the facilitator or an action item taker can help–is to acknowledge when a discussion ie. “we should refactor the reservation class based on the application’s bounded contexts” &lt;strong&gt;will not fit in the allocated timebox and agree to have a separate meeting dedicated to that topic&lt;/strong&gt;. You must be clear about the purpose of the followup meeting. Is it to share information? Advance the thinking? Provide input? Make decisions? Improve communication? These goals are from Sam Kaner’s “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Facilitators-Participatory-Decision-Making-Jossey-bass-Management/dp/1118404955&quot;&gt;Facilitator’s guide to participatory decision making&lt;/a&gt;” another great resource about having clear meeting is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Where-Action-Meetings-Break-Organization/dp/1732205205&quot;&gt;Where the action is&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pick-a-retrospective-topic&quot;&gt;Pick a retrospective topic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach would be to focus the retrospective on a topic agreed with the team before the meeting–but that assume there was some preparation. When we focus the retrospective someone in the group might still want to talk about off-topic items. If people feel strongly about sharing something with the group let them do it. I think a better strategy is to run daily 10 minutes retrospectives–for teams of 4 or 5–so the team has space to share information during the week and focus on overarching issues during the iteration retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preparedness&quot;&gt;Preparedness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retrospective is a meeting and to run a good meeting you need a clear purpose and some preparation.  Your plan might not survive contact with the team–and their evershifting context–so it’s ok to improvise at that point. &lt;strong&gt;The facilitator should not go in and improvise activities by default or come in unprepared&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going in to retrospective without a clue of what happened during the iteration should be an exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In small (5/6 people teams) I like to prevent that by taking one-on-one time with the group before retrospective to see what’s on their mind and prepare a retrospective plan that fits where they are at this time. For larger teams you can collect information with the help of co-facilitators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once was in a retrospective where the facilitator was trying to explain Jean Tabaka’s Sailboat activity while reading it on the phone. The group was pretty confused. When I pick up a new activity I write down a little script to explain the activity purpose and what the individuals are expected  to do. If it involves drawing I practice it beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think too often people focus on the retrospective activity rather than on the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;know-your-retrospective-framework-instead-of-activities&quot;&gt;Know your retrospective framework instead of activities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A framework gives structure to your retrospective and a clear start and end. I base my retrospectives plans on Derby/Larsen’s 5 steps framework and I pick activities that fit the group’s journey. I’ll briefly describe the 5 steps and you can look up other options like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lucidmeetings.com/glossary/orid&quot;&gt;ORID&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icacan.org/&quot;&gt;The institute of cultural affairs&lt;/a&gt;or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/resources/adaptive-action.html&quot;&gt;Adaptive Action&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;Human system dynamics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set the stage&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;: the group understands the goal of the retrospective, the room has psychological safety, roles are assigned, team norms acknowledged&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather data&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;: ensures the group is on the same page about what happened about the topic we’re focused on or the timespawn we’re looking at. The outcome should be a snapshot of all perspectives about what happened and hopefully mutual understanding. If the group doesn’t reach mutual understanding I’d spend more time until you get there. Reading “Facilitator’s guide to participatory decision-making” can give strategies to bring a group to mutual understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generate insights&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;: the group finds focus on a topic with affinity mapping, polling, prioritization to allow the team to go past the immediate solutioning and have a deeper conversation about no more than 1/2 topics. The outcome should be a set of ideas to formalise into an experiment for change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decide what to do&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;: the group comes up with a specific, measurable and time bound experiment (aka action item) or acknowledging if the topic is too broad and the time left during retrospective is not sufficient to come up with a detailed plan. If so schedule a followup meeting with its purpose and its desired outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Close out&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;: the group acknowledges what was achieved in the meeting and is clear about next steps and responsibilities. Now is a good time to end on a high note with a round of &lt;a href=&quot;https://retromat.org/en/?id=15&quot;&gt;appreciation&lt;/a&gt;. To speed up time in larger groups you can try having folks share appreciations via post-it notes or Jurgen Appelo’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://management30.com/practice/kudo-cards/&quot;&gt;Kudos cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great time to run a quick retro on your retrospective, I use a +ΔROTI. ROTI came from Esther Derby and it’s a Return Of Time Invested activity where you collect between 0 to 4 how well spent the time was. I ask the group to write the number on a post it note, and add a short sentence next to a Δ sign for the one improvement that would have made their ROTI go up by 1, and a short sentence next to a + for something they liked about today’s retro
    - 0: complete waste of time, I learned nothing
    - 1: mostly a waste of time but I learned one thing
    - 2: broke even, satisfactory retrospective
    - 3: better then an average, I learned quite a few things
    - 4: awesome, best retrospective of my life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to learn more about the framework read Derby/Larsen’s book about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;“Agile Retrospectives”&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to learn the origin of the 5 steps framework you can listen to my interview with Diana Larsen on my Retrospective facilitation podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-five-steps-retrospective-framework&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboration&quot;&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the facilitator you’re not alone. If the retrospective is in a safe environment and there is a purpose and you are prepared the group should be there to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re trying to juggle time keeping, note taking and action item collection while facilitating you can ask for volunteers for those tasks! That way there is a shared ownership of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are the facilitator but also a team member–scrum master/product manager/lead/whatever–you have a hard job to keep your biases under control. I know I do as the team product manager–and previously principal engineer–I had very strong opinions on team topics we talked in retrospective I was facilitating. When I had something that I felt was critical for the group to hear I would say: “I am taking my facilitator hat off and as a PM I think…”. I usually try to keep it to a brief sentence to give more colour and then go back to my facilitator role unless more context is required. It might be good to have a backup facilitator if you feel your stakes are too high and you might not be an impartial facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can ensure there is collaboration by having silent activities. For example instead of having an open discussion–where introverts and less loud people would be having a harder time contributing–use an activity like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liberatingstructures.com/1-1-2-4-all/&quot;&gt;1-2-4-all&lt;/a&gt;. Its purpose, having individuals brainstorm–ideas or topic–alone, then in pairs, then 4 then with the whole group. There are a multitude of activities out there, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liberatingstructures.com&quot;&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://retromat.org&quot;&gt;Retromat&lt;/a&gt; are good repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the facilitator skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage full participation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Promote mutual understanding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foster inclusive solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cultivate shared responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a retrospective to become more effective your organization and team should foster &lt;strong&gt;psychological safety&lt;/strong&gt;, as the facilitator try to &lt;strong&gt;prepare&lt;/strong&gt; and define a clear retrospective &lt;strong&gt;purpose&lt;/strong&gt; to ensure the group stays engaged and takes on targeted action items. Ultimately a retrospective requires &lt;strong&gt;collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; and the facilitator (you?) is there to make sure the ride goes smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to tackle organizational issues remember the team is part of a system. Look up Larsen/Shore’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.agilefluency.org&quot;&gt;agile fluency&lt;/a&gt; maturity model and Snowden’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://cognitive-edge.com/videos/cynefin-framework-introduction/&quot;&gt;Cynefin&lt;/a&gt; sense making framework for seeing issues and contexts from different lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources out there if you’re interested in the topic of reflection, retrospectives and facilitation. Here’s a few links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;Derby/Larsen Agile retrospectives book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Retrospective-Handbook-guide-agile-teams/dp/1480247871&quot;&gt;Kua’s The Retrospective Handbook: A guide for agile teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Facilitators-Participatory-Decision-Making-Jossey-bass-Management/dp/1118404955&quot;&gt;Kaner’s Facilitator’s Guide to Participatory Decision-Making&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.retrium.com/ultimate-guide-to-agile-retrospectives/intro&quot;&gt;Retrium’s video guide to retrospectives by David Horowitz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/about&quot;&gt;Retrospectives Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What challenges do you face in your retrospectives? What are the part of this post that you won’t be able to use? Why?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://teotti.com/make-your-retrospective-facilitation-even-more-effective-here-4-things-to-look-at/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://teotti.com/make-your-retrospective-facilitation-even-more-effective-here-4-things-to-look-at/</guid>
        
        <category>retrospectives</category>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
        <category>agile</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
